Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and today we're
going to be looking at the hydrolysis
reaction of amides with acids and bases.
So in this particular reaction we're
going to go through this and show how
this reaction can be done in two steps.
So the whole idea of this is we're going
to be cutting an amide into a carboxylic
acid and an amine for our first step
and then the second step is how will
one of the products be neutralized.
Depending on the conditions
set forth in the reaction.
So if we have an acid in the reaction,
we're going to neutralize the amine.
If we have a base in the reaction,
we're going to neutralize the
carboxylic acid that is being created.
So let's take a look at this and
let's see if we can, we'll go through
a bunch of different examples and
try to understand it right here.
Let's go through the steps.
All
right, in order to do a hydrolysis in
two steps, the first part has to do with
the name hydrolysis, which if you kind
of break that apart, hydro, Means water
and lysis means to cut which you commonly
see in a lot of Biological practices
is that cutting or breaking of things?
So we're gonna cut it with water.
So exactly what does that mean?
So if you think of the structure of water,
what we're gonna be doing is we're gonna
be looking at an amide right here So
we're gonna be cutting right in between
the C double bond O and the nitrogen
portion of the amide And what we're going
to be doing, we're going to be cutting
that with our little water scissors.
So when we use the blue scissors,
that is referring to using water.
Now if you think the structure of water
is H2O or HOH, so there's two components
of this that we're going to be adding.
We have the OH part, and then we
have the hydrogen component that
are going to be used For this
cutting, so one part is going to be
added to make the carboxylic acid.
The other part is going to be added
to the amine, to make the amine.
Now whenever we see this reaction, this
is typically done under heated conditions.
That's going to be kind of dissolving and
melting this compound and this question
mark here means that while depending on
if it's an acid or a base, there's going
to be a second step of the reaction.
So I left it just as a question mark
for now because we'll do, we'll show
how that's done in the next step.
First, let's just cut it.
So we're going to be making
our two individual pieces,
so let's copy those over.
So if we are to cut the left
from the right, so let's put the
left here, and then we'll have
the right hand side as well.
So they are going to be
separated as a result.
Now, being that they are separate,
we'll put a little plus sign to say,
hey, these two things are separate.
And what we're going to be doing
is adding the H components in OH.
So on the left side, we're going to be
making a carboxylic acid, and then on
the right side we're going to be making
an amine as part of our molecules.
So you see the amine on the right,
and then the carboxylic acid.
So every time this goes through
hydrolysis, we're always going to
be making these two components.
So let's take a look at the next step,
which has to do with neutralization
and how exactly we can try to
neutralize these two components.
So if we have, let's say a carboxylic
acid or an amine, we can neutralize them.
Being that if you remember from general
chemistry or even your organic class.
The carboxylic acid is the
acid and the amine is the base.
So let's look first, we're going
to look at the amine first.
So the amine, like I mentioned
before, this is our organic base.
So this is what we are
going to be neutralizing.
So the big tip here that I like
to always remind students is that
remember acids are proton donors.
bases are proton acceptors.
So right here we have hydrochloric
acid reacting with an amine.
HCl is one of your strong acids, meaning
that it's going to donate a proton.
So we'll write a little H plus
being thrown or given to the amine.
The amine will receive it.
So this will be the second step if
it's in an acidic condition where all
of a sudden what we'll do is we'll
write that RH with the amine just like
before, but the only difference is
we're going to now add a extra hydrogen.
So I notice how we went from 2 to 3.
And what we will do is we'll put a
positive charge on the nitrogen to
let it know that hey, it accepted
an extra hydrogen, which went on
the lone pairs of the nitrogen atom.
So that's all we have to do is show
how that one proton gets donated.
So if you have an acid hydrolysis,
it's a little bit easier.
Let's take a look at if you
had basic conditions for your
question mark in your problem.
So if we had base hydrolysis, well,
it's going to be a very similar idea.
I'm thinking that, Oh, well, we're going
to be cutting this with water like before,
but we're going to be neutralizing the
carboxylic acid portion with a base.
So the tip I like to use for this version
is think of a double replacement reaction.
Which, if you go back to introductory
chemistry or gen chem, that was
all about swapping charges, doing
that little bit of a swappy swappy,
double replacement, or trading.
So if we look at this reaction, we
can label the different portions.
So if you think, if hydrogen
is generally considered to be a
plus, oxygen is usually a minus.
We can also label the same thing
on sodium and hydroxide as well.
So what we're going to be doing is we're
going to be trading positive components,
kind of the same idea as if you ever watch
sports and you want to trade players or
trade draft picks or anything like that.
We are going to be trading
these two components.
Now, when this happens, the carboxylic
acid is going to become a salt.
And we're also going to be
making a salt and water.
So when we have an acid base
reaction, salt and water is created.
So we will have our, um, C double
bond O with an O minus now.
So you have to put that charge next
to Na plus as one of our compounds.
So this is known as a carboxylate salt.
So that A T E ending That is being
created, and our other portion
is going to be water, as we'll
have H bound to OH as our other
portion, or as you know it as water.
Now to go back to the one from earlier,
I forgot to name that, so if we have
a carboxylate salt that forms from
a base reaction, when we do the acid
reaction, this time we're going to have
what we refer to as an ammonium salt.
So when we have that NH3 Cl near each
other, so this is an ammonium salt.
So if we do acid hydrolysis, we
make an ammonium salt, and if
we do Base hydrolysis, we make
a carboxylate salt, alright?
So, this is kind of the idea.
Let's go through some practice
problems and put this to the test.
And we'll do both examples, so that
way you get plenty of practice problems
to be able to do this on your own.
Alright, let's take a look.
Alright, so on the following
problem, what we are going to be
doing is predicting and drawing the
products for the following reactions.
So, on this first problem, we can see that
we have an amide that is here, so we're
going to be going through hydrolysis, we
see the heating condition, and we also
see that we're going to be adding sodium
hydroxide as well to this reaction.
The first thing you need to do is
identify where your functional group
is, so you can see exactly where you're
going to be cutting it, so we can see our
amide right here highlighted in orange.
Now, what we're going to be doing is
cutting that part of the reaction,
so if we put our little scissors
right here, we are going to be
cutting this particular bond.
Now, meaning that on our left side we'll
have a carboxylic acid, and on the right
side we're going to be having an amine.
So the first thing I like to
do is I like to just draw each
of those functional groups.
So we'll do step one.
So we'll rewrite our left side of the
chain, so we got CH3, CH2, CH, with a
methyl, then we have that C double bond
O, attached to our water portion, which
was an OH, which was used to cut that.
Now the other portion is an Amin,
which we're gonna add a hydrogen
to it with the NH two from before.
So we can kind of simplify
that to be NH3 or ammonia.
Now what, being that this has a basic
condition that's being applied to this
reaction, what is it gonna react with?
Well, on the top here, we have an acid
right on the bottom we have a base.
So a base is gonna react with an acid.
Okay, so it's going to react with this
top species up here being that the
sodium hydroxide will react with that.
So the second step is when I take
that reactant and I'm going to
react it with sodium hydroxide.
And this will be your final product.
So just so you know, the amine
that formed earlier This thing
is already one of your answers.
So that's one of the pieces, but we need
to, we need to now make the other part.
So this is going to be that swap.
That's the complete double replacement.
So we're trading the
positive portions here.
So the Na is going to trade with the
hydrogen to make that carboxylic salt.
So let's take that.
We're going to erase the O, or the H,
being that now it's going to be replaced
with Na We'll write our charges in.
And this will be our answer
here as our, as our final thing.
So we have our carboxylic salt and we'll
also have water as a product as well.
So if you need to write that water
is here, we also made H2O2 as well.
So we made ammonia gas.
H2O and then our carboxylate salt.
So we made all these little
different products from this
particular reaction here.
Now, what about if I did the
same reaction and I had, um,
an acid that was being added?
What would have changed
with this reaction?
Well, if we were to cut it like we did all
the way up top, we're going to have the
same exact kind of idea here is we would
cut it in the same exact spot, right?
We would cut it right by the amide
bond, we would be making NH3,
and then that carboxyl, and then
the carboxylic acid from before
going through that process, right?
Now, what would be different is
the final step of the reaction.
We would still have our carboxylic
acid, but our amine, our ammonia
this time, or our amine in future
problems, It's going to react with HCl.
So if that were to happen,
we would do NH3 plus HCl.
And what do acids do?
Well, they donate a proton.
So we would show that proton
being given, making NH4 plus.
and Cl as a result, so it makes the
ammonium salt as a final answer.
So it just all depends on
how you look at it, right?
Whether you make an ammonium salt
or the carboxylate salt, it depends
on if it's acidic or if it's basic.
If it's acidic, amines react.
If it's basic, the carboxylic acid
reacts with the basic portion.
What about the following?
So if I do this reaction, what
exactly is going to happen?
Well, let's break it down into steps.
The first step we are going to
do, and let's make some room for
ourselves so we're not getting all
bogged down in the same area, is
we are going to do two exact steps.
So where are you going
to be cutting your bond?
So if we look, we can see that, all right,
here is the amide portion of the bond.
So we're going to be cutting it.
Right between the nitrogen and
the C double bond O right here.
So when we do that, we are going to
be making a Essentially a benzoic acid
and then an amine compound as a result.
So let's do that So we need to draw
the benzene ring So we'll draw our six
member ring and then we will write the
center here the C double bond O With
an OH attachment just like so and then
the other part we will have our amine
chain So we have our H, our N We'll
redraw the methyl and then the butyl
portion of the amine So we have these two
pieces that are forming as a result now
being that we're adding an HCl molecule
to this Well, what do we have to do?
We have to neutralize a part
Well, HCl is an acid, so that
means it's gonna be reacting with
the base, which is our amine.
So in step number two, we are going
to have, the amine is going to react
with HCl to make which product.
So let's see if we do plus HCl hydrogen
is going to be donated to that mean.
So what will we have?
Alls we do is add H two N.
We'll put a little plus sign
on it and then we will keep
all of our carbons right.
None of the carbons change.
The only thing that's changing
is the functional group.
It's going from an AM mean
to an ammonium as a result.
So we made an ammonium salt, and
depending on your teacher, sometimes
you might have to add the CL minus
next to it being that you have that.
Plus there must be a minus
and a carboxylic acid.
So just to kind of square off what
we made, We got that carboxylic acid
and then ammonium salt as our two
pieces of the puzzle that you made.
Let's do one last problem.
So with our last one, what is
going to be happening here?
Once again, we're going to be
doing that hydrolysis reaction.
So we're going to be cutting it right
between the N and the C double bond O.
So making those two
individual components, right?
So we'll have a carboxylic
acid on the left hand side.
We'll be adding our OH.
So we see that and now on the other part
we're going to be having our Hydrogen that
we added from water with the CH3 group.
Now, being that this is under basic
conditions, what side of the reaction
will the sodium hydroxide react with?
Well, being that acids neutralize
bases, the sodium hydroxide is going
to react with the carboxylic acid part.
So, it's going to react with the lect.
So that means that we can kind of start
boxing off some of our answers, right?
This portion, this is one of our
answers, so we'll keep that where it is.
Now the sodium hydroxide, how do
we look at that as before, right?
We're gonna be trading positive
charges, so we're gonna be putting a
plus on our hydrogen, on our sodium,
they're going to do a little trade.
And as a result, we will make CH3, C
double bond O, with O minus and Na plus.
Um, and another, there's another way
to look at this reaction too, how
to get to this final product, that
this is another way to help you see
how to get the carboxylate salt.
So, if you have, let's say, the CH3, C
double bond O, OH, you can also think
of it like a condensation reaction too.
It's not 100 percent the most
correct way to do it, but it
will get you the right answer.
So, if I turn around my sodium hydroxide.
So let's say if I put this
in red just to color code it.
So just as a final tip,
Condensation reactions, you
remove water, right, or H2O.
So if we see this reaction, we got H2O
here, we can actually remove water from
our reaction, right, so H2O is a product.
And then we're going to combine
the different pieces here.
So this is another way to get
the same answer if you're not
a big fan of trading charges.
You can also think of it in
terms of removing a water
as a condensation reaction.
So, it's just another way
of doing the same problem.
It just depends on how does
your brain work, when are you
looking at these problems.
Personally, I like trading the charges,
but I do know a lot of people like having
condensation, being that's a really big
part of organic and biochemistry examples.
I hope that this video helped.
Hydrolysis reactions are a tough reaction
to learn, but if you practice it, just
remember you're cutting with water and
then you have to neutralize one of the
products with whatever the condition is.
So if we're adding an acid to
this reaction, so this is kind of.
Go back up, so if we are adding an
acid with like HCl, that is going to
be reacting with the amine portion,
right, so the HCl donates the
proton, creating an ammonium salt.
If it's base hydrolysis, then that's when
we have to think of trading charges, and
it's going to react with the carboxylic
acid, so an acid base reaction.
Okay, I hope this video helped and
I hope to see you on the future.
Please hit that like and subscribe
button if it did help you and I hope
to see you all for future videos.
Thank you so much for watching and
hope you all have a wonderful day.